# NATHANIEL CLAUSE

J 270-978-6570 Columbus, OH ■ nate.clause@gmail.com ♠ https://github.com/NateClause

# Summary

I am a Mathematics PhD candidate at The Ohio State University, with experience in algorithm development, implementation, and testing using Python, C, and MATLAB. I am pursuing quantitative research positions in the financial sector where I can use my skills in mathematical and creative reasoning, critical thinking and machine learning to develop and optimize trading strategies. For further information, see my linkedin: https://www.linkedin.com/in/nathaniel-clause.

### Skills

Languages and Platforms: Python, MATLAB, C, Linux, LaTeX, HTML, SQL, Tableau

Libraries: Numpy, Scipy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Tensorflow, Keras

Quantitative: Data Analysis, Machine learning, Graph Theory, Probability, Combinatorics, Optimization Soft skills: Problem-Solving, Organization, Collaboration, Written and Verbal Communication, Leadership

## Experience

## The Ohio State University

August 2018 - August 2019, August 2023 - present

Graduate Research Fellow

Columbus, OH

- Performed research projects in topological data analysis under Dr. Facundo Mémoli whilst supported by the Distinguished University Fellowship at The Ohio State University.
- Introduced new invariants for multiparameter persistence and hierarchical clustering, and developed and implemented algorithms for their computation.
- Wrote 5 academic papers in journals or in submission, and gave 20 academic talks at conferences/seminars.

## The Ohio State University

August 2019 – August 2023

Graduate Teaching Assistant

- Taught 1 semester as lead instructor and 7 semesters as teaching assistant, for  $\sim$ 60 students per semester.
- Structured course syllabi and generated course materials including writing lectures, homeworks, exams and projects, and proctored and graded various assessments.

# **Selected Projects**

## Classification of Flocking Behaviors | Python

August 2019 - February 2020

- Created and implemented algorithms for computing betti functions and rank invariants for persistent homology of dynamic metric spaces (DMS), alongside zigzag persistence.
- Implemented an adjusted boids model to simulate flocking behavior, and used the model to generate thousands of DMS of flocking behaviors within five different behavioral classes.
- Performed a classification experiment on this data with the aforementioned invariants, utilizing a k-nearest neighbor classifier resulting in a classification accuracy of over 97%.

#### LSTM Stock Price Predictor | Python

February 2024

- Implemented an LSTM model in Python using the tensorflow library to predict future stock prices.
- Designed and implemented a mid-frequency trading strategy based on trading signals given by the model.
- Tested the trading strategy on holdout data from 100 stocks over two year timespans, consistently demonstrating annual returns over 200% higher compared to holding the stock from beginning to end.

### Leadership

### Network Data Analysis Group

June 2019 - present

Coordinator

The Ohio State University

- Organized weekly meetings for the network data analysis group, preparing discussion content and organizing speakers.
- Managed the group's website: https://ndag.github.io/index.html, updating the group's achievements.
- Gave at least one oral presentation per semester in the group meetings, ranging from 30 minutes to 90 minutes.

## Topology, Geometry, and Data Analysis Seminar

August 2023 - present

 ${\it Co-Coordinator}$ 

The Ohio State University

• Organized regular meetings for the TGDA seminar, inviting speakers and organizing travel arrangements for them.

## Education

### The Ohio State University

PhD in Mathematics

Expected Graduation: May 2024

Columbus, OH

Vanderbilt University

August 2014 - May 2018

Bachelor of the Arts in Mathematics, Highest Honors in Mathematics, Larsen award recipient

Nashville, TN